<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of sundry particular wicked plots and cruel, inhumaine, perfidious; yea, vnnaturall practises of the Spaniards Chiefly against the seuenteen prouinces of the Netherlands: yea, before they tooke vp armes. Gathered and translated out of seuerall Dutch writers, as that reuerend diuine Gulielmus Baudaitius, in his Morghen Wecker, and Emanuel de Miter, by S.O. a louer of truth and equity, and an vnfeigned hater of oppression and tyrannie, the bane of common-wealths.</title>
            <title>Adjoyner of sundry other particular wicked plots and cruel, inhumane, perfidious; yea unnaturall practises of the Spaniards</title>
            <author>Ofwod, Stephen.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18756</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121681</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856851</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856851</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22487</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08435)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22487)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1212:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of sundry particular wicked plots and cruel, inhumaine, perfidious; yea, vnnaturall practises of the Spaniards Chiefly against the seuenteen prouinces of the Netherlands: yea, before they tooke vp armes. Gathered and translated out of seuerall Dutch writers, as that reuerend diuine Gulielmus Baudaitius, in his Morghen Wecker, and Emanuel de Miter, by S.O. a louer of truth and equity, and an vnfeigned hater of oppression and tyrannie, the bane of common-wealths.</title>
                  <title>Adjoyner of sundry other particular wicked plots and cruel, inhumane, perfidious; yea unnaturall practises of the Spaniards</title>
                  <author>Ofwod, Stephen.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed, anno 1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reprinted from the second part of Verheiden, Jacob. An oration or speech appropriated unto the mightie and illustrious princes of Christendom (STC 18837), "An adjoyner of sundry other particular wicked plots and cruel, inhumane, perfidious; yea unnaturall practises of the Spaniards"--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Suggested place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22487:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22487:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF SVNDRY PARTICVLAR WICKED PLOTS AND CRVEL, inhumaine, perfidious; yea, vnnaturall practiſes of the Spaniards.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CHIEFLY</hi> AGAINST THE SEVENTEEN Prouinces of the <hi>Netherlands:</hi> yea, before they tooke vp Armes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>GATHERED</hi> AND TRANSLATED OVT OF Seuerall Dutch Writers, as that Reuerend Diuine <hi>Guliel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Baudaitius,</hi> in his <hi>Morghen Wecker,</hi> and <hi>Emanuel de Miter,</hi> by <hi>S. O.</hi> a louer of truth and equity, and an vnfeigned hater of oppreſſion and tyrannie, the bane of <hi>Common-wealths.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EXOD. 1.8.9.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The new King ouer Egypt ſaid vnto his people, concerning the Iſraelites, <hi>Gods people;</hi> Come on let vs deale wiſely with them, leſt they multiply.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM. 2.4.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that ſitteth in heauens ſhall laugh, the Lord ſhall haue them in deriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall he ſpeake vnto them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed, Anno 1624.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:22487:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22487:2"/>
            <head>To the wel-affected indifferent Reader.</head>
            <p>GEntle Reader, there being ſo much ſpoken as thou maiſt perceiue, by the fore-going Treatiſe, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cruel, inhumane, treacherous, perfidious; yea, vnnaturall practiſes of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in theſe parts, and elſewhere, which may ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineate him in his deſerued colours, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer beholds him may mourne to ſee this <hi>Hazael</hi> ſo to tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize ouer the innocent, and that the Lord ſhould permit, and the earth beare ſuch an vnheard of monſter; yet notwithſtanding much more might be added in ſundry other particulars, as the Dutch Chronicles mention, and other Writers haue well ſet out: amongſt which, although I my ſelfe be a ſtranger by Nation to them; yet ſince the time of my abode here, hauing attained ſome vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the Language, I haue thought fit to adde ſome further particulars, which in my reading I haue obſerued, and could adde many more; but my purpoſe being onely to annex a few things, I will not enlarge, leſt I adde another Treatiſe. But before I come to what I intend, I haue thought fit hauing ſome overſight in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of this Treatiſe aforegoing, to note by the way, the ill tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating of one word, in the 21 folio, it is touching the Princeſſe of <hi>Parma,</hi> the Tranſlator termes her <hi>a crafty Queene,</hi> whereas the word beares no ſuch ſence in the Dutch, but ſignifies one that hath a ſharp wit to deceiue, as is ſaid of the ſerpent that beguiled <hi>Eue.</hi> Beſide,<note place="margin">The Dutch word <hi>Ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſante</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour or Meſſenger.</note> that that is tranſlated <hi>Embaſſadour,</hi> ſpeaking of ſuch as were ſent from the States to the King, I conceiue to be more fittingly rendred <hi>Meſſenger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, thou art to vnderſtand, gentle Reader, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was louingly receiued here in the 17 Prouinces, and a ſolemn oath was taken on both parts; the King for his part ſwore to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine all their Lawes and Priuiledges, and they to him all due homage and allegance: He preſently demanded of them ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, whereupon the States did aſſemble, and collected for him 40
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22487:3"/>millions of Florines, of <hi>Brabants</hi> money, to be paid in nine yeares, and they paid it into his Exchequer; and although it was more then they had paid before to his predeceſſours, yet vpon this he did take great diſpleaſure againſt them; and, as they write, he for this did hate them to death.</p>
            <p>But he pretended this to be the cauſe of his wroth, becauſe he ſaw that there were ſome among them, that did defie the Pope and all his Religion: but that could not be, for the Citie of <hi>Aelſt</hi> was as ſuperſtitious in that Religion as <hi>Rome</hi> is ſelfe; for they did perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Reformed Religion euen vnto death: and yet for all that both they, and 170 faire villages that belonged vnto them, were by them plundered and ſpoyled of all their goods, and many of them wounded and tormented for to confeſſe where their money was, and many were killed. Thus much by the way.</p>
            <p>My ſcope and chiefe intent, is to ſhew the firſt and iuſt cauſe of the warres in the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> whereby the diligent Reader (not parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally affected) may clearely vnderſtand, that the <hi>Netherlands</hi> did not rebelliouſly take vp Armes againſt a lawfull Prince, (as ſome ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly thinke and ſpeake) but iuſtly and religiouſly defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt a perfidious Tyrant who ſought their ruine, by all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible meanes he could, and the ſubuerſion of the whole State. A long while they patiently vnderwent his cruell oppreſſions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable vexations, as the Hiſtories clearly manifeſt; till there was no helpe, but either they muſt become flaues in ſoule and body, worſe then that of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> they and theirs for euer, or elſe be butchered by mercileſſe executioners of a cruell Tyrant. This Tyrant hauing a purpoſe to innouate all things, to roote out the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient inhabitants, and to fruſtrate all the Lawes, Cuſtomes and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges which himſelfe had ſworn to maintaine, knew not how bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to effect his euill ends, then by rayſing a bloudy Inquiſition to ſet ouer them for their gouernment;<note place="margin">The inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition was here <hi>4</hi> years before.</note> which ſaid Inquiſition (raiſed in <hi>Spaine</hi>) concluded and pronounced certaine Articles, the tenth pr February 1568, which were confirmed by the King, the 16 fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. Now becauſe it may appeare I doe them no wrong in this charge, I will lay downe the Articles themſelues verbatim.</p>
            <p>The moſt ſacred Office of Inquiſition ſo often attempted in the Netherlands by his Maieſtie, and hindred vntill this time, ſhall bee
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22487:3"/>inſtituted and aduanced in this manner, which is moſt expedient.</p>
            <p n="1">1 They muſt perſwade the Emperour, being gone aſtray, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly confederated with heretikes, that hee reſigne his Kingdomes vnto his Sonne, with the whole adminiſtration of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That the Emperour with his two ſiſters, hauing giuen ouer all affaires, leauing the Netherlands, ſhall retire into Spaine vnto Vs, being aſſured that they ſhall neuer returne more to doe any harme.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Theſe being diſpatcht, we muſt alſo draw the king to vs, &amp; keep him for euer that he part not, and not ſuffer any Flemmings to haue acceſſe or conference with him.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That the King write vnto, and command the Clergie of the Netherlands, that with the Inquiſition they ſhould accept of 15 new Biſhops, the which ſhould be free from all ſecular iuriſdiction, yea in caſes of treaſon.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The ſubiects of the Netherlands through their malice and way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe, will reuolt and moue ſeditions and tumults, pleaſing to all but to our companie</p>
            <p n="6">6 The Princes and Noblemen, heads and authours of thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, with the ſubiects, muſt be taken away, and the others reduced vnto reaſon.</p>
            <p n="7">7 They ſhall hire at our charge theeues and ſpoilers of Churches and Images, whoſe offences ſhall be by all the world imputed to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, by ſome ſubtill meanes, and ſo we ſhall vanquiſh them.</p>
            <p n="8">8 That all Comerce, Negotiation, Liberties, and Priuileges, ſhall be rooted out, and that all be reduced to extreame pouertie, whereby the realme ſhall be permanent for Vs.</p>
            <p n="9">9 No man of all thoſe Countries (except he be of our faction) ſhall be held worthy to liue; and finally all to be rooted out: and all Goods, Poſſeſſions, Arts, and Trades, and all Orders to bee taken away, vntill there may bee a new Realme, and a new people.</p>
            <p n="10">10 In this action the wiſe and valiant Duke <hi>Alua</hi> ſhall be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in perſon; whereas any other, were he of the blood Royall, or a Prince, ſhall be of no eſteeme: ſo as being ſuſpect, yea in the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt matters, they muſt be diſpatcht.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:22487:4"/>
11 No Contracts, Rights, Promiſes, Donations, Oathes, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges, and ſolemne Aſſertions of the Netherlands, ſhall bee of any force for the inhabitants, as being guiltie of high treaſon.</p>
            <p n="12">12 But aboue al we muſt haue an eſpecial care that in theſe matters of ſo great weight and moment, wee proceed not violently, but by meanes, by degrees, and that diſcreetly, to the end the Princes, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, and inferiour ſubiects may mutinie amongſt themſelues, ſo that one may perſecute, yea execute the other vntill at laſt the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man be executed himſelfe. For in all Chriſtendome there is not a Nation more fooliſh and indiſcreet, and whoſe leuitie and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie may ſooner be deceived then theſe Netherlanders, and God puniſheth them accordingly.</p>
            <p>There were other Articles found in Preſident <hi>Vergaes</hi> chamber at <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> and there Printed; and thoſe are more cruel then theſe.</p>
            <p>By theſe articles and vnlimited power of theſe lawleſſe Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, noman had any aſſurance of life or goods for a day, but were In danger continually to be called in queſtion, either for the law of their God, or for ſome worke of mercie, which either religion, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall equitie, or the bond of nature called for: or elſe if they had co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour for none of theſe, they would impoſe ſuch vnreaſonable taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which if the Cormorants had not their gorges cramed full they would make prey of all, whether by right or wrong it mattered not. But my purpoſe being to avoyd prolixitie, and to paſſe by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinences and needleſſe repetitions, I will come to tnat I inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. In the yeere 1565 match was concluded for the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> and the nuptials were ſolemnized at <hi>Bruxels,</hi> whither all the Nobilitie and Gentry of the Countrey were inuited, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there met of them about foure hundred, who like faithfull <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> being grieued to ſee the dayly oppreſſion of their brethren by the hard task-maſters of the Inquiſition, who not onely robbed them of their goods, but alſo by inhumaine cruelty, and vnnaturall but chery, depriued them of their liues, who daily led them as ſheepe unto the ſlaughter: The conſideration hereof they ioyntly layd to heart, and hereupon (being met vpon this occaſion) they reſoved to preſent all petition to the Princeſſe of <hi>Parma,</hi> which they did the 5 of Aprill
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22487:4"/>next followings. The Earle of Breedrod deliuering the petition, humbly requeſted fauourable anſwer. Three dayes after they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued this anſwer, viz. they ſhould ſend two of their Noblement to the king, by whom ſhe would write in their behalfe. The Lord of Barlaymont being preſent, after their departure ſaid <hi>(like a flattering Courtier)</hi> they were a company of Raſcals and Beggars.</p>
            <p>It was concluded that the Marqueſſe of Bargen, and the Lord of Mountigny ſhould goe into Spain, who humbly preſented their ſuite to the King, but could get no anſwer in 16 moneths after.</p>
            <p>The 26 of Auguſt <hi>anno</hi> 1566, the Princeſſe of <hi>Parma</hi> ſent for the Gentrie, telling them ſhe had receiued letters from the King, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining promiſe that all ſhould be well, and that the Inquiſition ſhould ceaſe. And for the Proclamations they ſhould not be of force, but his Maieſtie would take ſuch order as they and the State ſhould like well of. The Princeſſe alſo gaue them toleration for their Religion, on condition they ſhould not deface, nor breake downe the ornaments of the Churches: for, there had beene before this time vilde and lewde perſons that freequented the meetings of the Reformed; theſe went into the Papiſts Churches, ſtole their ſiluer and what was worth carrying away, and brake downe their Images: but the Reformed ſuſpected that this was done by the appointment of the Princeſſe, neither was their ſuſpition without good ground,<note place="margin">Emanuel de Miter ſaith, that in Flanders they tooke <hi>50</hi> of them at one time, and hanged <hi>22</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the reſt.</note> for it is to be ſeen in the kings letters, <hi>Art.</hi> 7, that ſhe had order to hire this raskall company to doe this villany, which fact was imputed to the Proteſtants, to the end that they might not onely be odious there, but alſo ſeeme guilty, euen in the iudgement of other Nations; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the offenders were puniſhed with impriſoment, yea, with death, euen by the Reformed themſelues, who ioyntly confeſſed the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnlawfull, and were ſo farre from giuing occaſion of offence in this nature, that Papiſt Burgers themſelues offered good ſecurity that no ſuch thing ſhould be attempted by them. Who then can make any doubt that they were free from hauing any hand in thoſe outran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges layd to them, the very oppoſites in Religion being Iudges, who as appeares were willing to vndertake for them; now as their ſaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe brought ſo good effect for their perſons, ſo did the Lord worke that the truth of Religion found many friends likewiſe, the Lord wondrouſly proſpering the courſe of Reformation, in ſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22487:5"/>much that in ſhort ſpace they had in <hi>Flanders</hi> 60 Aſſemblies, ſome Churches they themſelues builded, but were by Duke <hi>d' Alua</hi> ſoon caſt downe, who errected gallowſes of them, and hanged them vpon them.</p>
            <p>The Princeſſe of <hi>Parma</hi> alſo began to entertaine ſouldiers with pretence to apprehend the Church-robbers, but intended indeed to take away the ancient Liberties and Priuiledges of the <hi>Netherlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> wherefore ſending certaine companies to <hi>Valencyn,</hi> the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants denyed them entertainment, who for that were proclaimed Rebels the 14 of December, ſoone after they were beſieged, ſacked, and many of them put to death.</p>
            <p>But before they of <hi>Valencyn</hi> denyed entertainment to the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the Nobility had received letters out of <hi>Spain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it for Religion, but his aime was to get their lands and goods.</note> from the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Bargen,</hi> ſhewing, that the King was exceedingly incenſed againſt the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> that he had in the preſence of many vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be fully reuenged of them, though it were with the hazard of all his Countries; that he would make them an example to all the world, and would inuite the Pope and Emperour to aſſiſt him in this quarrel. Vpon the receit of the letters the Nobility aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at <hi>Dortmond</hi> to conſult what were beſt to be done, but conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not any thing, ſome iudging it ſafeſt to ioyne, and make head to reſiſt his tyrannicall furie, other ſeeking rather to eſcape by flight.</p>
            <p>Now was the Inquiſition againe brought in contrary to the Lawes and Liberties of the Countrey, which the King was ſworne to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, for execution whereof there were appointed 12 Inquiſitors, commanding them to receiue the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> theſe were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The bloudy Councell,</hi> and ſo they were indeed, which <hi>Rome</hi> well knew, refuſing it, <hi>anno</hi> 1559, when as they fell vpon the Inquiſitors houſe, ſet it one fire, wounded the chiefe of them, brake open the priſon, and ſet at liberty the captaiues, and would haue burned a Cloyſter that belonged vnto them, had they not been by faire means diſſwaded by two Lords in the Citie, <hi>viz, Marc. Antonio Colunus,</hi> and <hi>Iulio Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>Venice, Naples</hi> and <hi>Millaine,</hi> though they be Papiſts, would not ſuffer it; the Marchants of <hi>Lisbon</hi> who are as ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the Romiſh Religon as any in the world, yet they did offer
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22487:5"/>the King two millions and a halfe, that they might not haue it in their parts.</p>
            <p>Yet the crueltie of this Inquiſition did here increaſe, and many Souldiers came into the Countrey, that ſome of the Countrey for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke their houſes, and reſorted towards Freezland, and ſome did ſtay at home, and went to meet Duke <hi>Alva,</hi> and well-commed him into the countrey, and ſhewed him all the kindneſſe they could,<note place="margin">As the Graue of Egmond, and the Graue of Horn, and many of the Gentry at Bruſſels, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but he very ſhortly tooke off moſt of their heads, ſo that he did ſo terrifie the Inhabitants, that there fled out of the Countries more then an hundred thouſand houſhoulders, beſides many that were taken in flying, were taken and hanged, and all theſe had their goods confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the King.</p>
            <p>The Prince of Orange, and the Earle of Bredrod, and fiue Earles, eight Lords, and 50. Gentlemen, and they had ſome fiue thouſand of Souldiers being in Freeſland, but were moſt over-throwne by the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> his forces; ſo that were driuen to Embden land, and there prepared themſelues to the Sea.</p>
            <p>Now the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> did command all the Inhabitants to pay the hundreth penny of all their goods, and of all that was bought and ſold; the which ſome of the States did yeeld vnto: and then he commanded them to pay the twentith penny: and then he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the tenth penny of all things that were bought and ſold, ſo often as they ſhould be ſold. Some of the States did make their humble petition to the Duke, and to the Princes, ſhewing them that it would driue all Trading out of the Land. The Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> told them that he would haue it, though it did ruinate all the Land; but if he ſaw them willing to doe their beſt to pay it, he would deale favourably with them.<note place="margin">All the priſons were filled, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, as they were ſorced to prepare more, and filled them alſo.</note> But he ſayd that it was againſt the Kings ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour if they ſhould not pay it, ſeeing it was his pleaſure to require it. And now did the Inquiſition impriſon and execute many of the richer ſort, as well Papiſts as of the Reformed Church: and if they were rich there was no eſcaping for them. And whoſoever was found to haue any hand in way of ſuit and petition to haue the tenth penny to be remitted, they were adiudged to haue committed high treaſom againſt God and the King; and all theſe muſt forfeit life and goods to the King, and not any, of their children to enioy one penny worth of the ſame: but (poore Orphanes) they muſt begge their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22487:6"/>bread. And ſome that had beene buried certaine months, they cauſed them to be digged vp, and hanged on the gallowes, and ſome to be burned, becauſe they had not the ſacrament, and confeſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their death; but it was becauſe he would conſiſcate their goods to the King: yea when theſe inſatiable gold-thirſty and blood-thirſty wretches wanted colour to cover their iniuſtice and cruelty, they had their officious imps (falſe witneſſes) ſuborned by <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> to get <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths</hi> vineyard; witneſſe <hi>Martin Hutton,</hi> who was one of the Inquiſitors Clarkes, and (being committed to priſon) did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that hee had made many falſe teſtimonies againſt ſundry rich perſons, ſome whereof were of the Reformed Church. Here might fitly be brought in the hundred Marchants of <hi>Granado,</hi> who were of the Romane Religion, and were never other; what pretence had he to cauſe them to be murthered all in one night, and then preſently to command all their goods to be brought to his Treaſury or Exchequer, whoſe eſtate was worth more then 28 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand pound ſterling? Now as this tyrant was a devourer and deſtroyer of the liues of men, ſo did he preſume to vſurpe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not onely vpon civill ordinances, but vpon the things of God; ſo that thoſe that were married in the Reformed Church, he forced to be married againe: and if they were rich, hee tooke them from their husbands, and gaue them to his Souldiers to make prize of them. Thoſe that were baptized in the Reformed Church, he compelled to be baptized againe, contrary to Gods word, and to the decree of the ancient Councels, ſo that intollerable were the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens this cruell <hi>Pharaoh</hi> laid ſo exceſſiue was his crueltie, that he fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all places with bloud, <hi>bloud touching bloud,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeakes. For in ſmall townes he executed 50. and in great townes 200. and 300. or 400. And in places as men travelled from one towne to another, they might ſee many that his Souldiers had hung vp in trees to death, and ſome were worth 80. thouſsand guldens, and ſome leſſe: yea this tyrant did confiſcate ſo much lands and goods, as by his account ſent into <hi>Spaine,</hi> did amount yearly to 8 tun of money ſterling, beſides the many thouſands that he and his Souldiers had. All the money that he did exact out of this land <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 6. yeares, did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to more then 50. millions of Gold. And if any were knowne to haue any thing that did belong to any that were put to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22487:6"/>death, and had not brought it to the knowledge of the Inquiſition, they did looſe both life and goods: yea the 16 of February 1566. he gaue ſentence in his court at <hi>Madrill,</hi> that they were all traytors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and himſelfe. At Vtrecht he beheaded a widow that was 84. yeares old, becauſe ſhe had before lodged a preacher one night. whoſe living was worth foure thouſand guidens yearely. And at Maſtrich a father for lodging his ſon that he had not ſeene in a long time, that was fled for religion, was put to death. And at that place there was one put to death for giving a widow a peck of come for an almes, whoſe husband this bloody court had put to death. And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny women were put to death, becauſe they received their husbands in the night that were fled for religion; yea they haue killed women great with child, and ripped vp their bellies, and taken out the child and killed it: and ſome they haue fleyed aliue, and covered drummes heads with their skins, and ſome they haue tyed to a poſt, and made a ſmall fire round about them, and ſo roſted them to death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The like cruel they did at Oudwater.</note>At Naerden they received the Spaniards friendly into the towne, who promiſed them both their liues and goods; and as ſoone as they came in, they commanded them to come to the State-houſe without their Armes, the which they did, and the Spaniards gaue fire vpon them and murthered them all: and then they ran about in the town, and raviſhed the women, and after killed them and fired the towne The young children that lay in the cradle, they quartered them, and tooke them vpon their pikes, and ſo went vp and downe the towne, reioycing in their crueltie.</p>
            <p>Such ſavage cruelty is ſcarcely to be found in any Hiſtory, what Chriſtian heart can heare it, and not be affected with deepe ſorrow, yet behold ſome monſters herein haue bin found, that haue beene ſo farre from humanity herein, (for hee that hath humanity in him will commiſerate others calamities) that they haue applauded it, as if he had in all theſe outrages done God good ſervice. Amongſt the reſt, I ſhall content my ſelfe at preſent, but to name the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope, and one of his chiefe ſonnes in this buſineſſe. The Pope ſends his Legat to commend theſe ſo rare expioits, and cals this cruell Duke <hi>Alva</hi> his beloved ſon, ſends him a coſtly ſword, the hilts whereof were of gold, and a hat wrought with gold, and beſet with rich and coſtly ſtones, thanking him for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22487:7"/>his good ſervice in maintaining the Romiſh Religion, and ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of heretiks. Howbeit that his chiefe ſonne I mentioned (excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this man of ſinne, in the ſinne of cruelty, as if hee would verifie himſelfe to be ten fold more the child of Satan, then his father the Pope) thinkes not ſo well of it, his name <hi>Vergas,</hi> the Preſident of this bloudy Inquiſition; for going ſhortly after into <hi>Spaine,</hi> hee told the King, that he and Duke <hi>d' Alva,</hi> did marre all in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> by ſhewing ſo much mercy to thoſe people.</p>
            <p>Concerning this Duke <hi>d' Alva,</hi> of whoſe outrage and crueltie ſo many haue felt, and perfiduous dealing which many haue found by lamentable experience, whereby may eaſily appeare of what ſtamp his exceſſiue mercies are, even ſuch as the Wiſeman ſpeakes of, <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.10. <hi>the tendermercies of the wicked are cruel.</hi> In which hee prides. himſelfe,<note place="margin">Theſe words he ſpake at a banquet, as he ſat at the Table, reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing he had, done the King ſo good ſervice.</note> boaſting he had ſlaughtered eighteene thouſand and ſix hundred, in forme of juſtice, in ſix yeares times, and ten times ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny he and his Souldiers murthered otherwaies. And many more would he doubtleſſe haue murthered, had not the Lord reſtrayned and limited him, for his deſire herein was as hell, that cannot bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied: Witneſſe the purpoſe of his proceeding againſt the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of <hi>Bruxels,</hi> becauſe they did not collect the tenth peny ſo as be deſired. He ſware that he would haue it, and before he would let it fall or remit it, the Sunne and Moone ſhould leaue their ſhining, ſo he went to Bruſſels, and commanded the executioner to prepare ladders and ropes to hang vp that night in their doores 70. of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, and gaue them his warrant in writing what they ſhould be: But God in his providence prevented this his cruel purpoſe,<note place="margin">Anno <hi>1573.</hi> April. <hi>1.</hi> I haue inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced but <hi>4</hi> or <hi>5</hi> townes, but there were ſcarce any towne eſcaped their cruel pillaging, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they had bribed their Commanders with exceeding large gifts.</note> in that there came newes that the Graue of Mark hath taken in the Brill; ſo the tyrant did not goe forward with his bloody enterpriſes.</p>
            <p>Thus having given you a taſte of ſome of thoſe many things I haue obſerved concerning the intolerable oppreſſion, &amp; worſe then ſalvage cruelty of the Spaniards, exerciſed vpon the people, which they endured and laboured vnder the ſpace of ſixteene yeares; I will now leaue theſe cruel tyrants to the Lord for judgement, &amp; addreſſe my ſelfe to ſpeake ſormewhat further concerning this Earle of Mark, who had thoſe Gentlemen with him that fled. Before this hee had layne with his ſhipping in England, but the King of Spaine ſending his Embaſſadour to our Queens (who was then in peace with him)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22487:7"/>to deſire her that ſhe would not ſuffer his ſubiects to haue their harbour in her land, and that ſhe would not giue them or ſuffer them to haue any reliefe whereby they ſhould make head againſt him: and heere vpon the Queene ſent and commaunded them out of her har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; and ſhe commanded that they ſhould not be ſuffered to haue any proviſion in her coaſts, ſo that now they had no other meanes but onely God, who did in his mercie provide for them better then they expected. For they were purpoſed to haue gone for the Taſſel, and to haue taken ſome towne about that part; but when they came neere that part, they had wind contrary that they could not come there, ſo they went for the Maſe, and came with their ſhips before the Brill, artd there they went preſently and tooke it; yet the Duke of Alva had his forces in the towne, neere ſo many as they were, whom they preſently killed and chaſed out of the towne, and out of the Iland. The Prince of Orange being in France, and hearing what had happened he ſent them ſouldiers with as much ſpeed as could be out of France. And within one moneth after Duke Alva ſent cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine companies to Vilſhing to keepe that place ſtrong for himſelfe, and many of the commanders were come into the towne: So the Magiſtrates commanded the Citizens to come preſently vpon the Statehouſe; ſo they told them they muſt lodge the Spaniards in their houſes, and they knowing how they had vſed the Citizens in al pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they came, they told the magiſtrates they would not haue the Spaniards in their towne. The Magiſtrates asked them which of them it was that did refuſe to receiue them. They ſayd, All of them. So the Magiſtrates ſeeing them ſo earneſt againſt the Spaniards, they joyntly tooke their Armes, and killed and tooke priſoners all them that were in the town, &amp; with their Ordenance they ſhot at his ſhips where the Spaniards were and they made away. And of thoſe that were take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there were the names of about 80. that they had in writing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Duke Alva that dwelt in the Hand, that they ſhould put to death.<note place="margin">Hee had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed thoſe to be executed becauſe they were the chiefe that ſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the tenth peny.</note> So thoſe of the Brill ſent their ſouldiers with ſpeed to helpe them. And ſhortly the Prince of Orange came with forces and defended them; and ſome other townes ſeeing the crueltie of the Spaniards, forſooke the Spaniard, and joyned with them, and tooke the Prince of Orange to be their Protector, yet the States notwithſtanding did remaine in obedience to the King ſome ſeven yeares after.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:22487:8"/>
Againe it is further worthy to be noted, that theſe Provinces did three times ſend to the King their Noblemen, but could obtaine no mercy, and many more times they went to the Princeſſe of <hi>Parma,</hi> and made their humble petition for redreſſe of their oppreſſion, but could not obtaine any favour, then they made friends to the renowned Queene of England, and to the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> and to the Emperour, who did earneſtly entreat by their Embaſſadours for them. The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> anſwered their Embaſſadours with theſe words; he bad them tell their Maſters, <hi>That they ſhould meddle with their owne ſubiects, and not with his, for he knew well enough how to rule his ſubiects without their counſel.</hi> Now when our Queenes Maieſty found his vnreaſonableneſſe and cruelty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ann.</hi> 1575.</note> then and not before, ſhee aſſiſted them with Armes.</p>
            <p>His owne ſonne Prince <hi>Charles</hi> did intreat for them, that it would pleaſe him to let them haue their Lawes and Priviledges, and that they might not be oppreſſed; and withall he told his father that thoſe Countries did belong to him,<note place="margin">Marplam in his Chronicle Ann. <hi>1567.</hi>
               </note> and that they were given him at his Baptiſme, for the which his father ſent him to priſon, and he never came out againe. If the Lord would not haue forgot what <hi>Amalek</hi> did, long after, for ſmiting the weakeſt and hind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his people, how may wee in equity forget the infinite murthers, and ſpoyles, this cruell Tyrant hath executed where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he hath prevailed? And who can forget in ſpeciall that bloudie attempt againſt our ſelues, in the yeere 1588.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould trace this Tyrant from place to place, I ſhould runne in infinitum, having made the name of Chriſtianitie hatefull, by his crueltie, aganſt the Heathens that know not God further then the light of nature: for it is confeſſed by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> themſelues, that ſome of the cheife of the <hi>Indians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">They were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orted by a Popiſh Prieſt minde, that after this life, there was one place for ioy and another torment.</note> who were to be burnt to death, being told of heaven and hell, they asked whether the <hi>Spaniards</hi> went whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they dyed. It was anſwered to heaven, <hi>Oh then ſayd they, we will never come there, for we wil never come where the Spaniards are.</hi> But not to run ſo far, I will reſt content to keepe me within the bounds I chiefly intended concerning theſe Countries. When the Citizens of <hi>Leyden</hi> were in great extremity, by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a long ſieg, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> proffering conditions of peace, if ſo be they would yeeld vp the Citie and themſelue to them, they returned anſwer; <hi>Not while they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22487:8"/>had a right hand to hold the ſword, or a left to eat;</hi> but if they ſhould be driven to fall into their hands, they would rather burne the Citie and drowne themſelues, then to ſubmit to them, of whoſe perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe they had had ſo lamentable experience: and when ſome of the Citizens preſſed a yeelding, in reſpect of the extremity of famine, a Burger maſter, called <hi>Peter Adrianſon</hi> ſaid; <hi>Loving friends, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the famine is great, and that ſome doe die for want of food: yet rather let vs agree to eat vp one another, as it ſhall fall by lot, begin with me firſt, and divide me amongst you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> by the appointment of their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour did come into the Citie in battell-order, and marched vp and downe in their ſtreets, and ſhot into heir houſes, and made a tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous noiſe, as if they had beene ſo many devils, for one day and two nights, and tooke the keyes from the Magiſtrates,<note place="margin">They did this as well to the Spiritualtie, as to the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltie, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> excepted.</note> and ſet watch at the Ports; whereby they put the Citizens in ſo great feare, that many women with childe fell in travell, and ſome dyed with feare: and they went by 12. or 20. into the beſt houſes, and commanded them to prepare them the beſt cheere, as boyled and roſt, and other dainty diſhes, as they liſt to call for; and beſides beere, they would haue at leaſt two ſorts of Wine. And all the chiefeſt Citizens houſes had at leaſt ten of theſe gueſts. And all cryed out for money, and ſaid,<note place="margin">They did offer them two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in money, and the third in cloth, but they cryed all for money.</note> that they would haue 15. moneths pay, before they went out of the Citie of them; And the Magiſtrates told them that they would procure them in cloth, and apparel, and money the ſumme; but they all cryed out for money, &amp; that money they would haue before they went away; ſo at the laſt, the Magiſtrates got the money, which did amount to 400. thouſand Guldens. And the charge they were at, which theſe companions did coſt the Citizens, was 600. pound ſterling the day; and thus they were oppreſſed with them 28. dayes,<note place="margin">I doe make but a ſhort Relation of ſome of the cruelties they did againſt this Citie, yet there ſtands in the Chronicle, out quire of Paper of their further crueltie.</note> in which time they had made them all rich ſuites, ſome of ſattin and velvet, and ſome of cloth of gold: and one of them had a cuſhion of velvet, with theſe wordes in Letters of Gold. <hi>I am the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Bride well Maſter.</hi> And thus they got rid of them for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. And about two yeares after they came againe, and then they vſed the Citizens much more cruelly, for theſe divels did bring ſtraw, and ſet on fire, and put it into the houſes, whereby they ſet nine rich ſtreets on fire, and burnt them with many rich and coſtly goods, and rifled the Citizens of all their rich and coſtly iewels, and ſilver-workes, with their money, and three dayes did they torment
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22487:9"/>the Inhabitants for money: <note>That they are now and haue beene this <hi>30.</hi> years more qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, I eaſily yeeld it. But why? Not that they haue changed their former na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for they ſtill hold the former princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent, but being more ſubtill, and finding their Kingdome is more weakned, they dare not to preſume as formerly. In the yeare <hi>1580.</hi> the States proclaimed King <hi>Philip</hi> to haue loſt his right, by reaſon he violated his oath.</note> and in this time there was murthered of the Citizens aboue foure thouſand. The money they tooke at that time is reckoned for more then fortie tun of gold, beſides the Iewels and the loſſe they had by fire, was as much as the reſt. And thus was the beſt Citie of Marchants in Europe ruinated.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Riſell</hi> there was a Spaniard would force a rich woman to haue the vſe of her body, and the women cryed out for helpe, and her husband came, and two of his neighbours to helpe his wife, and they thruſt the Spaniard away, and he ran into the ſtreet and cryed <hi>Spaynea, Spaynea,</hi> and there came many Spaniſh Souldiers about him, and they ruſhed into the houſe, and tooke the man and his neighbours, and carried them before the Magiſtrates on the towne-houſe, where they were aſſembled, and there before them he complained of them to be rebels, and ſtirrers vp of vp-rores, and told the Magiſtrates that if they did not preſently put them to death, they would burne their towne, and execute them themſelues, wherevpon they durſt do no otherwiſe, but hanged two, and whipped the other.</p>
            <p>Divers things being manifeſted of the Spaniards crueltie, I will adde one inſtance of their trechery, and that of a famous perſon to his neereſt familiars: yea when he pretended ſweeteſt familiaritie and friendſhip. Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 6. a Spaniard by birth, invited divers Nobles &amp; Cardinals to a banket, with a purpoſe to poyſon them all. The meeteſt inſtrument he made choyce of to effect this, was a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard, one <hi>Caeſar Burgia,</hi> his ſworne ſervant. The Pope ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wonderfull pleaſant, to avoyde ſuſpition, and dranke a carouſe to them all; willing that his truſty ſervant to fill from ſuch a Bottle he knew well: which he did very effectually to the Pope himſelfe as well as to the reſt.<note place="margin">A Spaniards kindneſſe to his friends.</note> After the company was departed, the Pope percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by an alteration in himſelfe, what was done, and that he muſt die now alſo, ſaid to <hi>Burgia, This is a right Spaniſh tricke.</hi> It is written of them that they are ſo expert in theſe exployts, that if <hi>Iudas</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe were aliue, he might got to them to Schoole.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I doe beſeech the Lord to ſhew mercy to my natiue Country, that they may never come vnder the government of the Spaniards, and giue them hearts to repent of their tranſgreſſions, and that they may ſincerely imbrace the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt, to their endleſſe comfort, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to command in all ſervices, for the advancement of the truth of Ieſus Chriſt.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:22487:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
